Finding Aid for Faculty and Staff handbooks (University of Michigan), 1973-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Faculty and Staff handbooks (University of Michigan) 1973-2007
[Faculty and Staff handbooks (University of Michigan)]
05102 Bimu 2
The collection contains published faculty and staff handbooks the University of Michigan summarizing the policies and practices governing the university's employees from 1973 to the present.
0.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The handbooks represent a variety of authoring units. The handbooks have been brought together in this collection for convenience.
The material is open without restriction.
The first faculty handbook was published in September 1978 for instructional staff. It was created with the cooperation of various University Senate committees, the Academic Affairs Advisory Council, and the Office of Academic Affairs to provide a summary of employment policies and practices. The handbook served to orient new faculty to key policies and provided an easy reference source for continuing faculty.
The body of policies and practices governing faculty are derived from the direction of the Board Regents and executive officers of the university, as well as federal and state legislation, and principles and custom. This body of policies exists within several authoritative sources, including the university's Standard Practice Guide (SPG. The SPG is available online at: http://spg.umich.edu/), the Board of Regents' Proceedings (also available online at: http://www.umich.edu/~regents/), and policy directives from individual executive officers. These sources remained the authoritative versions of policies after the publication of the handbook.
Similar handbooks were published for the primary research staff (March 1982) and primary librarian staff (May 1984). The handbook for research staff was published as the interim version of what would become a joint faculty handbook for instructional and primary research staff. The first handbook published jointly for instructional and primary staff was issued in December 1994. It was published by the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Primary staff includes research scientists, archivists, curators and librarians.
The format of the handbook changed with the Fall 1998 faculty handbook, published by the Office of the Provost. The handbook was modified to become a navigational tool, indicating which sources had information on the various policies. This was also the first handbook published in both online and print form. The online version linked to the authoritative sources of the policies whenever electronic versions were available. For the Fall 2004 handbook, the online version was the complete authoritative handbook and the print version was abridged. As of August 2005, the online version is located at http://www.provost.umich.edu/faculty/handbook/
The staff handbooks serve the same role as the faculty handbooks, providing summary information on the various policies governing staff employees. The first handbooks, published ca. 1978, had different versions for professional and administrative staff, technical staff, and office staff. After 1985, there was a single handbook for allied health, office, professional and administrative, and technical staff. The staff handbook had been updated periodically in print form and is also available online. As of August 2005, the online version is located at http://www.umich.edu/~hraa/staffhandbook/
________________
Sources Consulted:
Faculty and staff handbooks (introductions and prefaces).
Michigan Daily, "Faculty hail 1st new handbook since '78 edition," March 2, 1995.
The collection contains published handbooks for University of Michigan faculty and staff members. It is divided into two series: Faculty Handbooks and Staff Handbooks. Publishers of the handbooks include the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action and the Office of the Provost.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Regulations.; University of Michigan--Employees.; University of Michigan. Personnel Office.; University of Michigan. Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Academic Affairs.; University of Michigan. Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs.; University of Michigan--Faculty--Handbooks, manuals, etc.
- Faculty Handbooks
  Faculty Handbooks (0.25 linear feet, 1974-2004) contains all published versions of the faculty handbooks, including instructional staff, primary research staff, and librarians. The handbooks include the administrative structure of the university, faculty governance, appointment policies, compensation, benefits, retirement, and various regulations. A 1974 draft is the earliest version. The handbooks are arranged in chronological order by date of publication. The printed version from Fall 2004 is abridged. The online version of the handbook is identified as the authoritative and complete version. An archival version of the digital faculty handbook is held by the Bentley Library at http://www.umich.edu/~bhlumrec/admin_unit/provost/provost.htm.
  - Information Guide for Instructional Staff, Draft #2 July 1974 (Box 1)
  - The University of Michigan Faculty Handbook:
    - Instructional Staff, September 1978 (Box 1)
    - Primary Research Staff, March 1982 (Box 1)
    - Primary Librarian Staff, May 1984 (Box 1)
  - The University of Michigan Faculty Handbook for Instructional and Primary Staff, December 1994 (Box 1)
  - The University of Michigan Faculty Handbook Ann Arbor Campus, Fall 1998, Fall 2001 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Handbook: The University of Michigan Ann Arbor Campus
    - Fall 2001 (Box 1)
    - Fall 2004
      - Print version (Box 1)
      - Digital version, html file
    - 2005, html file
    - 2006, html file
- Staff Handbooks
  Staff Handbooks (0.25 linear feet, 1973-1999) includes handbooks for professional and administrative personnel, clerical and office personnel, technical personnel, and allied health staff. Eventually the individual handbooks for different staff categories were merged into a single handbook. The handbooks contain information on job expectations, compensation, absence from work, benefits, and various regulations and policies. The handbooks are subdivided by categories and arranged in chronological order by date of publication. An archival version of the digital staff handbook is held by the Bentley Library and is available at the following URL: http://www.umich.edu/~bhlumrec/admin_unit/hraa/hraa.htm
  - Clerical Staff
    - Clerical Staff Handbook, circa 1978 (Box 1)
  - Office Personnel and Staff
    - Policy Handbook: Office Personnel, circa 1973 (Box 1)
    - Policy Handbook: Office Personnel (revised edition), March 1974 (Box 1)
    - Office Staff Handbook, April 1981 (Box 1)
  - Professional and Administrative Staff
    - Professional and Administrative Staff Handbook, circa 1978 (Box 1)
    - Professional and Administrative Staff Handbook, April 1981 (Box 1)
  - Technical Personnel and Staff
    - Policy Handbook: Technical Personnel, circa 1973 (Box 1)
    - Policy Handbook: Technical Personnel (revised edition), March 1974 (Box 1)
    - Technical Staff Handbook, circa 1978 (Box 1)
  - Staff Handbook for Allied Health, Office, Professional/Administrative, and Technical Staff
    - The University of Michigan Staff Handbook: Allied Health, Office, Professional/Administrative, Technical, 1985 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Staff Handbook: Allied Health, Office, Professional/Administrative, and Technical, September 1990 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Staff Handbook for Allied Health, Office, Professional/Administrative and Technical Staff Members, December 1993 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Staff Handbook for Allied Health, Office, Professional Administrative and Technical Staff Members, August 1999 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Staff Handbook (Box 1)
    - 2005, html file
    - 2007, html file